<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc
  SYSTEM '../../clonk.dtd'>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../clonk.xsl"?>
<doc>
  <title>Diagnostic Messages</title>
  <h>Diagnostic Messages</h>
  <part>
    <text>
      Certain constructs may be flagged by the engine as potentially
      unintended or deprecated. In these cases, the engine will, by default,
      emit a warning to the log file.
    </text>
    <text>
      On occasion, these constructs are in fact intended by the script
      author. In order to avoid unwanted warning messages hiding more important
      messages, the engine supports selectively suppressing a warning category
      for parts of a script.
    </text>
  </part>
  <part>
    <text>
      Suppression and re-enablement is handled by the <code>#warning</code>
      directive. The directive must be placed on a separate line.
    </text>
    <text>Warnings can be controlled using this syntax:</text>
    <code>#warning {enable|disable} [warning_category [warning_category...]]</code>
    <text>
      If no category is given, the engine will suppress or enable all messages,
      including those that are not enabled by default. A category remains
      disabled or enabled until the next directive that affects it, or until
      the end of the script. A script linked to via the <code>#include</code>
      or <code>#appendto</code> directives does not affect, and is itself not
      affected by, the warning settings of the current script.
    </text>
    <text>
      It is not an error to specify a category that does not exist; the
      invalid category is simply ignored. No separate warning is emitted.
    </text>
  </part>
  <part>
    <h>Warning Categories</h>
    <text>The following warning categories currently exist:</text>
    <table>
      <rowh>
        <col>Category</col>
        <col>Description</col>
      </rowh>
      <row>
        <col>invalid_escape_sequence</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            The engine found an escape sequence inside a string that it
            did not recognize.
          </text>
          <part><code>"\p"</code></part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>invalid_hex_escape</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            The engine found the start of a hexadecimal escape sequence
            inside a string, but no hexadecimal digits followed it.
          </text>
          <part><code>"\xGN"</code></part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>type_name_used_as_par_name</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            A function parameter was declared without an explicit type
            specification, but with a name that is the same as a built-in type.
          </text>
          <part><code>func f(array)</code></part>
          <text>
            This warning is not enabled by default.
            <a href="#fn1" title="The warning may be enabled by default in a future version.">ยน</a>
          </text>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>empty_parameter_in_call</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            In a function call, a parameter was left empty. The engine is
            passing <code>nil</code> in its place.
          </text>
          <part><code><funclink>CreateObject</funclink>(Clonk,, 30, 100);</code></part>
          <text>
            This warning is not enabled by default.
            <a href="#fn1" title="The warning may be enabled by default in a future version.">ยน</a>
          </text>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>empty_parameter_in_array</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            In an array literal, an entry was left empty. The engine is
            using <code>nil</code> in its place.
          </text>
          <part><code>[1, 2,, 3, 4]</code></part>
          <text>
            This warning is not enabled by default.
            <a href="#fn1" title="The warning may be enabled by default in a future version.">ยน</a>
          </text>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>implicit_range_loop_var_decl</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            The loop variable of a for-in loop was not declared either in the
            loop header itself nor in the containing function. This is only
            accepted for backwards compatibility and may be removed in a
            future release. Explicitly declare the variable by adding the
            <code>var</code> keyword.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code>func f() {
&#9;for (i in [1, 2, 3]) {
&#9;}
}</code>
          </part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>non_global_var_is_never_const</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            A variable has been declared as <code>const</code>, but is not
            global. At this time, non-global variables are always mutable.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code>const local a = {}</code>
          </part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>variable_shadows_variable</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            The declaration of a variable uses the same name as a variable
            in a greater scope. Changes to the shadowing variable will not
            affect the shadowed variable.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code>static foo;
func f() {
&#9;var foo = 3;
}</code>
          </part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>redeclaration</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            A variable has been redeclared in the same scope. Make sure
            you do not accidentally overwrite values another part of the
            code relies upon.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code>func f() {
&#9;var i;
&#9;var i;
}</code>
          </part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>variable_out_of_scope</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            A variable has been used outside of the block it has been
            declared in. This is accepted only for backwards compatibility
            and may be removed in a future release.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code>func f(a) {
&#9;i = 0;
&#9;if (a) {
&#9;&#9;var i = 1;
&#9;}
&#9;return i;
}</code>
          </part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>undeclared_varargs</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            Use of <code><funclink>Par</funclink></code> inside a function
            implicitly declares it as using a variable number of arguments.
            This is not immediately obvious to callers of the function, and
            should be explicitly declared in the function signature by
            adding a final <code>...</code> parameter.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code>func f(a) {
&#9;return <funclink>Par</funclink>(a);
}
// Better:
func g(a, ...) {
&#9;return <funclink>Par</funclink>(a);
}</code>
          </part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>arg_count_mismatch</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            A function call passes more parameters than the function will
            accept.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code><funclink>GetDir</funclink>(0)</code>
          </part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>arg_type_mismatch</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            The parameter given in a function call is of a different type
            than the called function expects. The call will likely fail at
            runtime.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code><funclink>Sin</funclink>("huh?")</code>
          </part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>empty_if</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            An <code>if</code> conditional is controlling an empty statement.
            Use the empty block <code>{}</code> if this is intentional, or
            remove the conditional entirely.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code>if (true);</code>
          </part>
        </col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>suspicious_assignment</col>
        <col>
          <text>
            An assignment was found where an expression was expected. While
            an assignment returns its own value, usually a comparison was
            intended instead.
          </text>
          <part>
            <code>if (a = b + 1) { /* Do something */}</code>
          </part>
          <text>
            If the assignment is intentional, make this more obvious by
            extracting it to a separate statement, or explicitly handle the
            boolean conversion by adding a comparison operator.
          </text>
        </col>
      </row>
    </table>
  </part>

  <part>
    <h>Examples</h>
    <examples>
      <example>
        <code>func f(string s) {
&#9;Sin(s);&#x9;// WARNING: parameter 0 of call to 'Sin' passes string (int expected)
#warning disable arg_type_mismatch
&#9;Sin(s);
#warning enable arg_type_mismatch
&#9;Sin(s);&#x9;// WARNING: parameter 0 of call to 'Sin' passes string (int expected)
}</code>
      </example>
    </examples>
  </part>
  
  <a id="fn1" style="font-size: smaller; color: inherit;">ยน The warning may be enabled by default in a future version.</a>
</doc>
