<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc
  SYSTEM '../../clonk.dtd'>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../clonk.xsl"?>
<doc>
  <title>Meshes</title>
  <h>Meshes</h>
  <part>
    <text>It is possible to directly use 3D models (meshes) as object graphics. To do so they need to be in OGRE format. For most modeling tools there exist exporter tools, a list can be found on the <a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/tikiwiki/tiki-index.php?page=OGRE%20Exporters">OGRE Wiki</a>. Both the OGRE binary format (*.mesh) and the OGRE XML format(*.mesh.xml) are supported, however it is recommended to always use the binary format whenever possible since it is smaller in size and can be loaded more quickly by the engine. The tool <a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/tikiwiki/tiki-index.php?page=OgreXmlConverter">OgreXMLConverter</a> can convert between the two formats.</text>
    <text>The exporter normally creates a mesh file (*.mesh or *.mesh.xml), a skeleton file (*.skeleton or *.skeleton.xml) if the mesh contains bones, a material script (*.material) and potentially used textures. To use the mesh as a Clonk object all generated files need to be copied into the <emlink href="definition/index.html">object definition</emlink> and the mesh file needs to be renamed to Graphics.mesh or Graphics.mesh.xml, respectively. Textures are supported in PNG, JPG and BMP format.</text>
    <text>The mesh is not automatically scaled to the shape (i.e. the width and height values specified in <emlink href="definition/defcore.html">DefCore.txt</emlink>) of the object. Instead one unit in the modeling tool corresponds to one pixel in Clonk. This simplifies using the same magnitude of object sizes for all objects which is especially helpful for attaching meshes (see below). Also pay attention to the coordinate frame: The X axis in the mesh coordinate frame points out of the screen in Clonk, the Y axis points to the right and the Z axis points upwards.</text>
    <h id="MaterialScripts">Material scripts</h>
    <text>All material scripts (*.material files) are loaded by the engine before the mesh in the same directory is loaded. Material scripts are simple text files which specify the material properties (material colors, textures, etc.) that can be used by meshes. Each material is assigned a name that can normally be specified in the modeling tool. It should be taken care that names are unique (for example by prefixing all material names with the object name of the object they are supposed to be used with) since all loaded materials can directly be used by any mesh so otherwise they could be naming conflicts.</text>
    <text>Material scripts can also be crafted or edited by hand. The format is described in the <a href="http://www.ogre3d.org/docs/manual/manual_14.html">OGRE manual</a>. However not all of the features described there are supported (yet): Especially pixel, vertex and geometry shaders cannot be used. Also usage of LOD (Level of Detail) is not yet possible. For the source1 and source2 fields in the colour_op_ex field in texture units the additional value src_player_colour can be specified to refer to the player color of the object's owner. This can be used to colorize objects (partly) by the player color.</text>
    <text>At runtime the material script can be changed using the C4Script function <funclink>SetMeshMaterial</funclink>.</text>
    <h id="Animations">Animations</h>
    <text>As for bitmap based graphics an object can play an animation while executing an action. To do so first a rig for the model and then an animation needs to be created. When exporting it is saved in the *.skeleton (or *.skeleton.xml for the OGRE XML format) file. To play it during an action the Animation field of the action needs to be set in the <emlink href="definition/actmap.html">ActMap</emlink>. The Facet fields are ignored for mesh graphics.</text>
    <text>It is also possible, via script, to play multiple animations at the same time or to specify transitions between animations. To learn more about this possibility see <emlink href="definition/animations.html">Animations</emlink>.</text>
    <h id="Attachment">Attachment of meshs</h>
    <text>Meshes can be attached to each other so that they always move together. This allows the clonk to carry objects or to aim with the bow. To attach two meshes the C4Script function <funclink>AttachMesh</funclink> can be used, or <funclink>DetachMesh</funclink> to detach them again. When attaching a bone of both meshes needs to be specified. The attached mesh is then aligned so that its bone has always the same position and orientation as the one to which it is attached.</text>
    <text>However it needs to be taken care of the fact that only the meshes, that is the graphics of the objects, are attached. The real position of the attached object (so what is returned by the functions <funclink>GetX</funclink> and <funclink>GetY</funclink> or the area in which the object is found by the functions <funclink>Find_AtPoint</funclink>, <funclink>Find_InRect</funclink> oder <funclink>Find_AtRect</funclink>) is <em>not</em> affected.</text>
    <h id="Picture">Picture graphics.</h>
    <text>If an object uses a mesh then the Picture entry of the <emlink href="definition/defcore.html">DefCore.txt</emlink> remains without effect. Instead a perspective projection of the mesh will be used. The camera will be placed in the front of the object at a distance so that the mesh is totally covered.</text>
    <text>The position and orientation of the mesh with respect to the camera can be changed by making use of the "PictureTransformation" property. This way it can be shown displaced, rotated or scaled. The property should be assigned an array with 12 integer entries which make up a 3x4 matrix. The first four values specify the first row, the next four values specify the second row and the last four entries specify the third one. Those matrices can be conveniently created using the script functions <funclink>Trans_Identity</funclink>, <funclink>Trans_Translate</funclink>, <funclink>Trans_Rotate</funclink>, <funclink>Trans_Scale</funclink> and <funclink>Trans_Mul</funclink>.</text>
    <text>As with <funclink>SetObjDrawTransform</funclink> the individual matrix elements are specified in per thousand (1000 = 100%) since there are no floating point numbers in Clonk.</text>
    <text>As an example we show the transformation of the tool workshop:</text>
    <code><funclink>SetProperty</funclink>(&quot;PictureTransformation&quot;, <funclink>Trans_Mul</funclink>(<funclink>Trans_Translate</funclink>(0,0,7000), <funclink>Trans_Rotate</funclink>(-20,1,0,0), <funclink>Trans_Rotate</funclink>(30,0,1,0)), def);</code>
    <text>First the workshop is rotated by 30 degrees counter-clockwise around the Y axis, then by 20 degrees clockwise around the X axis. Finally it is moved 7 units in positive Z direction so that it is nearer to the camera.</text>
    <h id="Transformation">MeshTransformation</h>
    <text>The same way the "PictureTransformation" property affects the presentation of the picture graphics the "MeshTransformation" property is applied for ingame graphics. The results are very similar to what can be done with <funclink>SetObjDrawTransform</funclink>, however there are a few subtle differences:</text>
    <ul>
      <li>With the "MeshTransformation" property the Z coordinate can be influenced. So for example the mesh can be rotated around the X or Y axis.</li>
      <li><funclink>SetObjDrawTransform</funclink> is applied after lighting. The transformed coordinates have no influence on the lighting anymore. So for example if the mesh is illuminated from below and then is turned upside down by <funclink>SetObjDrawTransform</funclink> then the illuminated spot is at the same position on the mesh, that is it is also rotated. When using the "MeshTransformation" property however the lighting is applied after the transformation so that the mesh is always illuminated from below, no matter how it is oriented.</li>
      <li>If both "MeshTransformation" and <funclink>SetObjDrawTransform</funclink> are set then first the "MeshTransformation" is applied to the mesh and then <funclink>SetObjDrawTransform</funclink>.</li>
    </ul>
  </part>
  <author>Clonk-Karl</author><date>2010-04</date>
</doc>
