<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE funcs
  SYSTEM '../../../clonk.dtd'>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../clonk.xsl"?>
<funcs>
  <func>
    <title>CreateEffect</title>
    <category>Effects</category>
    <version>8.0 OC</version>
    <syntax>
      <rtype>proplist</rtype>
      <params>
        <param>
          <type>proplist</type>
          <name>prototype</name>
	  <desc>A proplist containing the callback functions for the new Effect. The name (<funclink>GetName</funclink>) of this proplist becomes the name of the effect.</desc>
        </param>
        <param>
          <type>int</type>
          <name>priority</name>
          <desc>Effect priority. Must be greater than zero.</desc>
        </param>
        <param>
          <type>int</type>
          <name>timer</name>
          <optional />
          <desc>Interval for the timer calls. With <code>nil</code>, no timer calls are made and the effect stays on permanently until it is deleted by other calls.</desc>
        </param>
        <param>
          <type>any</type>
          <name>var1</name>
          <optional />
	  <desc>First extra parameter to be passed to <code>Construction</code>, <code>Start</code> and <code>Effect</code> callbacks.</desc>
        </param>
        <param>
          <type>any</type>
          <name>var2</name>
          <optional />
	  <desc>Second extra parameter to be passed to <code>Construction</code>, <code>Start</code> and <code>Effect</code> callbacks.</desc>
        </param>
        <param>
          <type>any</type>
          <name>var3</name>
          <optional />
	  <desc>Third extra parameter to be passed to <code>Construction</code>, <code>Start</code> and <code>Effect</code> callbacks.</desc>
        </param>
        <param>
          <type>any</type>
          <name>var4</name>
          <optional />
	  <desc>Fourth extra parameter to be passed to <code>Construction</code>, <code>Start</code> and <code>Effect</code> callbacks.</desc>
        </param>
      </params>
    </syntax>
    <desc>Creates an effect. Returns the effect if successful or <code>nil</code> if not (e.g. because the effect was rejected). If the effect was accepted by another effect which is deleting itself within the same call, the return value is probably <code>nil</code>. Effects can be created on objects, <code>Global</code> and <code>Scenario</code>. This is passed as the first parameter to the effect callbacks.
</desc>
    <remark>For examples and more information see the <emlink href="script/Effects.html">effects documentation</emlink>.</remark>
    <related>
      <emlink href="script/Effects.html">Effects Documentation</emlink>
      <funclink>CheckEffect</funclink>
      <funclink>GetEffectCount</funclink>
      <funclink>EffectCall</funclink>
      <funclink>GetEffect</funclink>
      <funclink>RemoveEffect</funclink>
    </related>
  </func>
  <author>Sven2</author><date>2004-03</date>
  <author>Günther</author><date>2014</date>
</funcs>
