<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc
  SYSTEM '../../clonk.dtd'>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../clonk.xsl"?>
<doc>
  <title>Teams.txt</title>
  <h id="Scenariotxt">Teams.txt</h>
  <text>Via the Teams.txt component you can specify in which way groups of players play with or against together in multiplayer melees. From 4.9.6.0 CR.</text>
  <text>
    <table>
      <caption id="SektionTeams">Section [Teams]</caption>
      <rowh>
        <col>Value</col>
        <col>Data type</col>
        <col>Description</col>
        <col>Default value</col>
      </rowh>
      <row>
        <col>Active</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>0 or 1. If 0, no teams exist and it is assumed that no teams can be formed at runtime. This also means that no hostility options will be available in the player menu.</col>
        <col>1</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>AllowHostilityChange</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>0 or 1. If 1, players can declare hostility or alliance at runtime.</col>
        <col>0 if Teams.txt is present. 1 if Teams.txt is not present but the melee rule is active.</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>AllowTeamSwitch</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>0 or 1. If 1, players can choose a different team at runtime.</col>
        <col>0</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>AutoGenerateTeams</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>0 or 1. If 1, players can declare hostility or alliance at runtime.</col>
        <col>0 is there are team sections present. 1 if there are none.</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>TeamDistribution</col>
        <col>Identifier</col>
        <col>Player distribution to the teams. Possible values are: Free (free choice), Host (the host chooses during lobby), Random (random distribution) or RandomInv (random distribution, but not displayed during lobby).</col>
        <col>Free</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>TeamColors</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>0 or 1. If 1, all players of a team are assigned the same color.</col>
        <col>0</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>MaxScriptPlayers</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>Maximum number of script players which the host can activate in the lobby of network games. This includes script players that have already joined.</col>
        <col>0</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>ScriptPlayerNames</col>
        <col>String</col>
        <col>A list of names separated by "|" which are assigned to script players joinging in the lobby. If no list of names is provided, all script players are called "Computer".</col>
        <col>Computer</col>
      </row>
    </table>
  </text>
  <text>
    <table>
      <caption id="SektionTeam">Any number of sections [Team]</caption>
      <rowh>
        <col>Value</col>
        <col>Data type</col>
        <col>Description</col>
        <col>Default value</col>
      </rowh>
      <row>
        <col>id</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>Identifier: a unique number greater than 0 which can be used to identify a team in scenario scripts. Usually you can simply use ascending numerical values as team identifiers.</col>
        <col>Must be specified!</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>Name</col>
        <col>String (max. 30 chars)</col>
        <col>Team name. You can also specify localized strings such as $TeamRight$. See <emlink href="lang.html#Teamstxt">Localization</emlink>.</col>
        <col></col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>PlrStartIndex</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>If not 0, all members of this team use the corresponding [PlayerX] section in <emlink href="scenario/scenario.html#SektionenPlayer1Player2Player3Player4">Scenario.txt</emlink> for starting conditions. If 0, starting conditions are assigned automatically and independent of team membership.</col>
        <col>0</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>Color</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>32 bit RGB value of the team color. The team color is used instead of the player color if TeamColors is set.</col>
        <col>0</col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>IconSpec</col>
        <col>String</col>
        <col>Specifies a team icon for runtime joins or non-network games.</col>
        <col></col>
      </row>
      <row>
        <col>MaxPlayer</col>
        <col>Integer</col>
        <col>Maximum number of players who may join this team. 0 for infinite.</col>
        <col>0</col>
      </row>
    </table>
  </text>
  <author>Sven2</author><date>2006-06</date>
</doc>
